A Guide to the Papers of the White and Holland families of Fluvanna County, Virginia, 1839-1859
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the White and Holland families of Fluvanna County, Virginia 1839-1859
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11356-a
ca. 640 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the University of Virginia Library from the Book Broker, Charlottesville, Virginia on October 7, 2002.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 640 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot), 1839-1959, pertaining to the Holland and White families of Fluvanna County, Virginia, including correspondence, business and legal papers, genealogical information, and printed material.
The correspondence includes a letter from John Bragg of Richmond to John C. Holland, May 25, 1841, discussing Holland's purchase of a machine (see related item in accession #11356, letter from John Bragg, January 1841). Letters dated August 28, 1861 and March 14, 1862 discuss military service. An October 26, 1843 letter from Daniel Bentley to John White announces his own imminent arrival in Fluvanna from Kentucky with hogs for sale. An August 7, 1849 letter to John White from his daughter encourages him not to remarry after the death of his wife. In an April 7, 1861 letter, A. J. Perry inquires about Aunt Sally's estate. A letter dated January 29, 1865 from John H. White, a soldier, to his parents mentions "great talk here about peace."
Letters dated March 28, 1967 and February 6, 1868 discuss the settlement of the estate of Robert Kent. An August 29, 1881 letter from William R. Keilton of Abbeville County, South Carolina, offers Mrs. S. J. Perkins a situation as a governess. A letter, April 22, 1884, expresses condolences to Brother White on the death of his daughter, Miss Lucy. Other topics of correspondence include fashion and dressmaking, cooking and recipes, health, weather, and farming. Some letters are incomplete because pages or envelopes are missing and others have had notes written on them at a later date. When possible, undated correspondence has been sorted by recipient.
Included in the financial papers is a receipt dated June 25, 1863 for the sale of "one negro man named Major." There are tax records and cancelled checks as well as receipts for purchase of cloth and other sewing supplies, shoes, and groceries. The legal papers include documents related to the settlement of the estate of Sarah Stone, Nicholson v. Perry, and Perkins v. Bell. The miscellaneous folder includes fabric samples, sewing patterns, a school notebook, a singing society contract, and Arm & Hammer Baking Soda collectable animal cards.
Related names: Emma Anderson, Frances Baskett, Daniel Bentley, John Bragg, John C. Holland, Lucy M. Holland, Richard Holland, Robert S. Holland, Sarah Holland, Judson Kent, Sarah E. Kent, Sallie Perkins, A.J. Perry, A.L. Shepherd, Sarah Stone, Ino White, J. Bernard White, James P. White, John White, Lucie (Lucy) White, Sadie Lou (Sadelew) White, Sallie J. White, Willie White.
Arrangement
These papers are arranged chronologically within folders and alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Christmas cards and decorations n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Correspondence 1839-1849 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Correspondence 1850-1859 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Correspondence 1860-1869 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Correspondence 1870-1879 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Correspondence 1880-1889 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Correspondence 1890-1899 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Correspondence 1900-1909 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Correspondence 1910-1919 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Correspondence 1920-1959 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Correspondence to Sallie Perkins, Lucy White, and Willie White n.d. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Correspondence to Lucy White n.d.
- Family history n.d. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Family history - lineage of Kate Flanagan McGuire n.d.
- Family history - descendants of Richard P. White and Mary Meriwether through 1944 1945
- Financial 1840-1859 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Financial 1860-1869 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Financial 1870-1879 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Financial 1880-1899 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Financial 1900-1926 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Financial n.d. (Box-folder 2:7)
- Financial 1863, 2 items
- Ledger 1865 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Legal 1864-1872 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Militia roll - Company no. 1, 12th regiment, Virginia militia, J. C. Holland, Captain 1862 Mar 21 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box-folder 2:11)
- Newsclippings 1907, 1936, n.d. (Box-folder 2:12)
- Notebook listing financial transactions of the White and Holland and other families, ca. 1840-1870 n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Photographs (unidentified) n.d. (Box-folder 2:14)
- Poetry and other writings n.d. (Box-folder 2:15)
- Wills of Martha Richardson, Robert Kent 1832, 1861 (Box-folder 2:16)